South Boston Neighborhood House. Records of the South Boston Neighborhood House, 1861-1996 (inclusive), 1940-1980 (bulk): A Finding Aid
Records of the South Boston Neighborhood House, 1861-1996 (inclusive), 1940-1980 (bulk).
- Series II. ADMINISTRATION, 1931-1996, n.d. (#2.1-6.7, Vt-158.1)
  - Subseries A. Board of directors, 1931-1996, n.d. (#2.1-4.9)
    - Minutes, January-November 1983, 4.2.
    - Minutes, January-October 1984, 4.3.
    - Minutes, April 1985 - December 1987, 4.4.
    - Minutes, January 1988 - December 1989, 4.5.
    - Minutes, January-December 1990, 4.6.
    - Minutes, January-December 1991, 4.7.
    - Minutes, January 1992 - December 1994, 4.8.
    - Minutes, January 1995 - June 1996, n.d., 4.9.
  - Subseries B, Executive committee, 1970-1996 (#7.1-7.6)
    - Minutes, October-November, 1970; includes essay and report on settlements, 7.1.
    - Minutes, April-September 1980, 7.2.
    - Minutes, December 1981 - September 1989; includes quarterly report, 7.3.
    - Quarterly reports, minutes, January 1990 - October 1992, 7.4.
    - Minutes, January 1993 - October 1994, 7.5.
    - Minutes, January 1995 - June 1996, 7.6.
  - Subseries C. Annual reports, 1940-1991 (#5.1-5.5)
    - Annual reports, 1940-1949, 5.1.
    - Annual reports, 1950-1959, 5.2.
    - Annual reports, 1960-1961, 5.3.
    - Annual reports, 1984-1987, 5.4.
    - Annual report highlights, 1990-1991, 5.5.
  - Subseries D. Annual meetings of the corporation, 1932-1995 (#5.6-6.7, Vt-158.1)
    - Minutes, October 1932 - December 1958, 5.6.
    - Minutes, January 1959 - October 1961; includes case studies, 5.7.
    - Minutes, May 1966 - May 1970; includes speech Settlements in the War on Poverty, presented at annual meeting., 5.8.
    - Minutes, June 1971 - November 1978, 5.9.
    - Minutes, September-November 1979, 5.10.
    - Minutes, May 1980 - September 1982, 5.11.
    - Minutes, May 1983 - June 1984, 5.12.
    - Minutes, April-November 1985, 6.1.
    - Minutes, June 1986 - December 1987, 6.2.
    - Minutes, January-October 1988, 6.3.
    - Minutes, September 1989 - October 1990, 6.4.
    - Minutes, November 1991 - November 1992, 6.5.
    - Minutes, October 1993 - November 1994, 6.6.
    - Minutes, November 1995, 6.7.
    - Taped ceremony of award presented to Kenneth S. Brecher, President of the William Penn Foundation, at annual meeting, n.d., Vt-158.1.
      REQUEST AS Vt-158, reel 1.
- Series III. COMMITTEE FILES, 1947-1995, n.d. (#7.7-8.8)
  - Subseries A, Program committee, 1977-1985 (#7.7-7.10)
    - Minutes, January 1977 - December 1979, 7.7.
    - Minutes, March 1980 - February 1981, n.d.; includes program evaluations, 7.8.
    - Minutes, March-October 1981, 7.9.
    - Minutes, January 1984 - April 1985, 7.10.
  - Subseries B. Fundraising, budget and finance committees, 1980-1989 (#7.11-7.12)
    - Minutes, March 1980 - December 1981, 7.11.
    - Minutes, October 1985 - December 1989; includes committee objectives, financial report, 7.12.
  - Subseries C. Board membership, organization and nominating committees, 1970-1982, n.d. (#8.1-8.2)
    - Minutes, April 1970 - November 1979; includes memoranda, by-laws, reports, 8.1.
    - Reports of the nominating committee, March 1980 - September 1982, 8.2.
  - Subseries D. Personnel committee, 1960-1995 (#8.3-8.5)
    - Memoranda, November 1960 - April 1964; includes job descriptions, 8.3.
    - Minutes, April 1980 - December 1991; includes meeting agendas, job descriptions, correspondence, memoranda, and personnel policies, 8.4.
    - Personnel policies, June 1992 - June 1995, 8.5.
  - Subseries E. House council and miscellaneous committees, 1947-1961 (#8.6-8.8)
    - House council statement of purpose, 1947-1948, n.d; includes house council report, constitution and by-laws of the Denison House Council, 8.6.
    - Brochure listing members of the golden anniversary planning committee, 1952, 8.7.
    - Report of the Committee on Expansion of the Olivia James House, November 1961, 8.8.
- Series IV. GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1952-1994 (#8.9-8.12)
  - Correspondence, April 1952 - March 1958, 8.9.
  - Correspondence, January 1967 - July 1989, 8.10.
  - Correspondence, May 1990 - April 1994., 8.11.
    Includes reference copy of photograph of John S. Howland, ca. 1960, original filed in #8.12
  - Photograph removed from #8.11, 8.12.
- Series V. FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1958-1993, n.d. (#9.1-11.5)
  - Subseries A. Operating expenses, 1961-1984 (#9.1-9.6)
    - Treasurer's report, 1961-1969; includes summary of expenses, budgets, invoices and check requests, 9.1.
    - Program report and audit, 1978-1979, 9.2.
    - Projected expenses, 1980-1984; includes comparative revenue sources, donor contributions, and financial statements., 9.3.
      CLOSED UNTIL JANUARY 1, 2034.
    - Hawks Memorial Fund, 1982-1983., 9.4.
    - Hawks Memorial Fund, 1982-1983., 9.5.
    - Contributions, 1982-1984., 9.6.
  - Subseries B. Fundraising activities, 1963-1992 (#9.7-9.13)
    - Development fund program, 1963-1964; includes guidelines, SBNH brochures, donor list, clippings., 9.7.
    - United Community Services fundraising policy, ca.1966, 9.8.
    - Correspondence, Friends of the South Boston Neighborhood House, 1977-1981; includes meeting notes, 9.9.
    - Correspondence, 1981-1984; includes invitation to SBNH Mortgage Burner's Dinner, memoranda, brochures and mailing list for SBNH Build a Future dinner campaign., 9.10.
      See #PD.27.
    - Correspondence, 1985-1989, 9.11.
    - Quarterly reports, 1990, 9.12.
    - Memoranda, quarterly report 1991-1992; includes proxy votes, 9.13.
  - Subseries C. Proposals and grants, 1958-1993, n.d. (#10.1-11.5)
    - Program reports and proposals, 1958-1973, 10.1.
    - Correspondence and reports related to West Broadway Task Force and United Way, 1974-1975, 10.2.
    - Proposal, Family Service Project, statement of case, 1975-1976, 10.3.
    - Reports and proposals, 1977-1980, 10.4.
    - Proposal related to Old Colony Task Force, 1981., 10.5.
      See #PD.20sl.
    - Proposed budget and allocation request for West Broadway Task Force (WBTF), 1981; includes WBTF newsletter, 10.6.
    - Correspondence, proposed partnership between WBTF and SBNH, 1982; includes newsletters, 10.7.
    - Proposals for adult education program, 1982-1984, n.d.; includes funding proposals to the Student Activities Committee of the University of Massachusetts, 10.8.
    - Correspondence related to program funding, 1983-1985, 10.9.
    - Correspondence related to grant funding for South Boston Summer Collaborative, 1986, 10.10.
    - Proposal for funding reorganization of SBNH board, 1986-1987, n.d., 11.1.
    - Correspondence related to grant funding, 1986-1987, 11.2.
    - SBNH long range plans and proposals submitted to the United Way of Massachusetts Bay, 1987, 11.3.
    - Correspondence, summary of expenses related to South Boston Summer Collaborative, 1987-1990, n.d., 11.4.
    - Correspondence, budget material related to South Boston Summer Collaborative, 1991-1993, n.d., 11.5.
- Series VI. PROGRAMS, 1940-1995, n.d. (#11.6-13.5)
  - Subseries A. Activities and annual events, 1940-1995, n.d. (#11.6-12.6)
    - Announcement for award night, Olivia James House yearbooks, 1940-1942, 11.6.
    - Programs and event flyers, 1945-1947, n.d, 11.7.
    - Tickets, programs and event flyers, 1948-1950; includes schedule for Griffin Friendly Club [the Mothers' Club]., 11.8.
      See #PD.3f
    - Programs, schedules, event flyers, 1951-1954, n.d; includes signage, 11.9.
    - Programs and event flyers, 1955-1958; includes invitation to opening of Homans House, 11.10.
    - Programs and event flyers, 1965-1970, 11.11.
    - Mission statement, programs, event flyers, brochures, 1978-1980, 11.12.
    - Programs and event flyers, 1981-1983; includes bumper sticker, 12.1.
    - Programs, brochures, invitations, and event flyers, 1984-1988, 12.2.
    - List of enrolled students, 1989-1990., 12.3.
      CLOSED UNTIL JANUARY 1, 2080.
    - Programs, event flyers, and newsletter, 1991-1992, 12.4.
    - Programs and event flyers, 1993-1994, 12.5.
    - Program brochures, flyers, 1995, n.d., 12.6.
  - Subseries B. Reports, regional studies and collaborative programs, 1959-1992, n.d. (#12.7-13.5)
    - Reports and programs, 1959-1968; includes planning studies, demographic guides, maps, and regional profile, 12.7.
    - Social service statistics and reports, 1974-1978, 12.8.
    - Boston population and housing studies, ca.1978-1979, 12.9.
    - Correspondence, program evaluation, and census report, 1979-1980, 12.10.
    - Correspondence, programs, and reports related to the Student Activities Committee of the University of Massachusetts, 1980-1981, 13.1.
    - Descriptive material for adult education program, letters supporting South Boston dispute settlement project, SBNH program evaluation, 1982-1985, 13.2.
    - Parental release forms, fee agreements related to the Children's Center, Inc., 1985-1986., 13.3.
      CLOSED UNTIL JANUARY 1, 2077.
    - Memoranda, contract, and correspondence pertaining to the Children's Center, Inc., 1986, 13.4.
    - SBNH mission statement and program goals, 1988-1992, n.d.; includes director's report and social service studies, 13.5.
- Series VII. PUBLICATIONS AND PUBLICITY, 1901-1994, n.d. (#13.6-15.15, E.1)
  - Subseries A. Newsletters, 1940-1994, n.d. (#13.6-13.11)
    - The James House Herald and Olivia James House Herald, 1940-1954, 13.6.
    - Ollie Action, Ollie News, and Neighborhood House News, 1972-1979; includes the West Broadway Task Force newsletter featuring SBNH event, 13.7.
    - South Boston Neighborhood House Newsletter, 1982, 13.8.
    - The Ollie Up-Date, Ollie Chronicle, and South Boston Neighborhood House Newsletter, 1988-1989, 13.9.
    - Ollie Chronicle and South Boston Neighborhood House Newsletter, 1990-1991, 13.10.
    - South Boston Neighborhood House Newsletter and The Ollie Kids' Newsletter, 1992-1994, n.d., 13.11.
  - Subseries B. Press releases and related, 1971-1990, n.d. (#13.12-14.8)
    - Press releases, 1971-1979, 13.12.
    - Press releases, 1980, 13.13.
    - Press releases, 1981, 14.1.
    - Press releases, 1982, 14.2.
    - Press releases, advertisements, feature articles, 1982, 14.3-14.4.
    - Press releases, advertisements, feature articles, 1983, 14.5-14.6.
    - Press releases, advertisements, feature articles, 1984, 14.7.
    - Press releases, 1988-1990, n.d., 14.8.
  - Subseries C. Reference files, 1901-1989, n.d. (#15.1-15.7)
    - Excerpts from the History of South Boston, by John J. Toomey, 1901, 15.1.
    - Essays and statement on settlements, 1946-1952; includes Settlements 60th Anniversary 1886-1946, Statement of Settlement Function, 15.2.
    - A Short History of St. Augustine's Cemetery, by William J. Gurney, 1953, 15.3.
    - Brochure and articles on settlements; includes Settlements in the United States - Past and Future, Bertram M. Beck, Social Work, 1964-1976, n.d., 15.4.
    - South Boston district profile, 1977-1983; includes Living in Boston, 15.5.
    - The Unfinished War [War on Poverty], by Nicholas Lemann, The Atlantic Monthly, 1988-1989, 15.6.
    - The Catholic Church and the Desegregation of Boston's Public Schools, James E. Glinski, New England Journal of Public Policy, ca.1988., 15.7.
  - Subseries D. Publicity, 1958-1992 (#15.8-15.15, E.1)
    - Speech given by John W. McCormack, Speaker of the House of Representatives, in recognition of SBNH's accomplishments, 1958, 15.8.
    - City and Neighborhood Resources for Residents of South Boston, 1979, n.d.; includes Greater Boston settlements guide, 15.9.
    - Greater Boston Settlement Week, published by the United Neighborhood Centers of America, 1980, 15.10.
    - Correspondence, questionnaire, and book excerpt from That Old Gang of Mine: The History of South Boston, 1900-Present, Patrick J. Loftus, Jr., ca.1985, 15.11.
    - South Boston Neighborhood House Data Source Booklet, 1988, 15.12.
    - Finding and Working with a Pro-Bono Agency [advertisement agencies], 1990, 15.13.
    - South Boston Neighborhood House, 90 years of community service, 1991; includes SBNH descriptive brochures, 15.14.
    - Revisiting the Settlement Idea, report of the Boston Foundation, 1992, 15.15.
    - Web site, 2010-ongoing., E.1
- Series VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS AND OVERSIZED MATERIALS, 1861-1994, n.d. (#PD.1z-PD.28, F+D.1-F+D.2, SD.1)
  - Subseries A. Photographs, 1922-1991, n.d. (#PD.1z-PD.28)
    - Milk glass portrait of young girl nicknamed Ollie, n.d. (1 photograph), PD.1z.
    - Youth and adult activities, 1933-1942, n.d. (17 photographs), PD.2.
    - The Mothers' Club, ca.1930s; includes Mrs. Homans (1 photograph), PD.3f.
    - Negative of photograph in #PD.3f; includes notes and reference copy., PD.4.
      FILED WITH NEGATIVES.
    - Youth and adult activities, 1943 (4 photographs), PD.5f.
    - Youth and teen activities, 1944-1949, n.d. (16 photographs), PD.6.
    - Youth and teen activities, ca.1950-1958, n.d. (6 photographs), PD.7.
    - Testimonial dinner for Ruth A. Bass, Greater Boston Council for Girl Scouts, September 1955 (1 photograph), PD.8o.
    - Various views of the South Boston Neighborhood House, 1922-1991, n.d.; includes photographs of renovations (12 photographs), PD.9.
    - Negative of photograph in #PD.9, PD.10.
    - Homans House Annex, 1945-1955, n.d. (8 photographs), PD.11.
    - Youth activities, 1956-1960, n.d; includes photograph of Mrs. Marian J. Homans (13 photographs), PD.12.
    - Youth activities; includes sports banquet with William Bulger, 1961-1974, n.d. (5 photographs), PD.13.
    - Negative of sports banquet photograph in #PD.13, PD.14.
    - Fundraising events, 1971-1991; includes James Hawks, former president of SBNH (19 photographs), PD.15.
    - Student busing for school desegregation, 1974-1975 (32 slides), PD.16sl.
      FILED WITH SLIDES.
    - SBNH programs, events and field trips, 1974-1980 (37 slides), PD.17sl.
    - Staff members, 1979-1992, n.d.; includes inscribed photograph from Raymond L. Flynn (11 photographs), PD.18.
    - Senior activities, 1980-1991, n.d.; includes ethnic folk dance, seniors scholarship award, and the Jet Set (11 photographs), PD.19.
    - Old Colony Housing Projects, ca.1981 (12 slides), PD.20sl.
    - Tour of South Boston, 1981 (60 slides), PD.21sl.
    - Youth activities, 1982-1992, n.d.; includes South Boston Against Drugs (SOBAD) program, and Southie clean-up (15 photographs), PD.22.
    - Ollie Classic Road Races, 1986-1991, n.d. (14 photographs), PD.23.
    - GED graduations, 1987-1991 (8 photographs), PD.24.
    - Annual meetings, 1989-1990; includes Sister Ann Fox, former executive director of SBNH, John Tynan, former SBNH President, Marian Wright Edelman, president of the Children's Defense Fund (11 photographs), PD.25.
    - SBNH multicultural summer, 1989 (48 photographs), PD.26fv+.
    - SBNH Board activities, 1991-1992; includes Mary Nee, John Tynan, William Bulger, and Raymond Flynn (4 photographs), PD.27.
    - Negatives without prints; Marian J. Homans, Ollie Road Race (2 negatives), PD.28.
  - Subseries B. Oversized materials, 1861-1994, n.d. (#F+D.1-F+D.2, SD.1)
    - Certificate for change of name, SBNH mortgages and deeds, 1861-1935, F+D.1.
    - Album cover with Olivia James House logo [separated from album], n.d., F+D.2.
    - Poster, mortgages, deeds, floor and land plans, 1962-1994, n.d., SD.1.
- SERIES IX. CLIPPINGS, 1926-1996, n.d. (#16.1-17.9)
  - Clippings, February 1926-1949; includes obituaries of Olivia and Ellerton James, 16.1.
  - Clippings, 1950-1960, 16.2.
  - Clippings, 1961-1970, 16.3.
  - Clippings, 1971-1981, 16.4.
  - Clippings, 1982, 16.5.
  - Clippings, 1983, 16.6.
  - Clippings, 1984, 16.7.
  - Clippings, 1985-1987, 16.8.
  - Clippings, January-September 1988, 16.9.
  - Clippings, September-December 1988, 16.10.
  - Clippings, January-June 1989, 16.11.
  - Clippings, 1989, 17.1.
  - Clippings, 1990, 17.2.
  - Clippings, 1990, 17.3.
  - Clippings, 1991, 17.4.
  - Clippings, 1991, 17.5.
  - Clippings, 1992, 17.6.
  - Clippings, 1992, 17.7.
  - Clippings, 1993, 17.8.
  - Clippings, 1994-1996, n.d., 17.9.
Additional catalog entries
The following catalog entries represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. An entry for each appears in the Harvard On Line Library Information System (HOLLIS) and other automated bibliographic databases. THIS IS NOT AN INDEX.
Authors
Homans, Marian J.
James, Olivia Buckminster
Subjects
Adult education--Massachusetts--Boston
Amateur theater
Americanization
Annual reports
Athletic clubs--Massachusetts--Boston
Blueprints
Boston (Mass.)--Clubs
Boston (Mass.)--Social conditions
Busing for school integration--Massachusetts--Boston
Camps--Massachusetts
Citizenship--Study and teaching--United States
Clubs--Massachusetts--Boston
Community centers--Massachusetts--Boston
Day care centers--Activity programs--United States
Deeds
Electronic records
Ethnic neighborhoods--Massachusetts--Boston
Family day care--Activity programs--Massachusetts
Home economics--Study and teaching--Massachusetts--Boston
Immigrants--Economic conditions--20th century
Immigrants--Education--Massachusetts--Boston
Immigrants--Family relationships
Immigrants--Massachusetts--Boston--Social conditions--20th century
Minutes
Older people--Services for--Massachusetts
Olivia James House (South Boston, Mass.)
Photographs
Social work with immigrants--Massachusetts--Boston
Social settlements--Massachusetts--Boston
Social workers--Massachusetts--Boston
South Boston (Boston, Mass.)--Economic conditions
Teenagers--Massachusetts--Boston--Societies and clubs
Web sites
Women social workers--Massachusetts--Boston
Women volunteers in social service--Massachusetts--Boston
Videotape
Vocational education--Massachusetts--Boston